you know you're taking some of the 300
principle you try to think okay what's
even more fundamental than that what's
behind that what's what's below that
what kind of feeds into that I have to
say
um also you won't get more fundamental
simple in the free energy principle when
you realize that your environment is
composed of other things very much like
you right
when you're young your mum or as your
older or your colleagues and your
friends and your family and I think
that's interesting because now we get
into a much more symmetrical
um sort of relationship between me and
the environment and certainly in this
context you know most of my universe is
basically you and me so now there's a
certain kind of symmetry in play
um whereas you are my environment and I
am your environment and yet we both have
Geraldine models of our environments
which basically means I have a
generative model of you and you have a
generative model of me the best way to
minimize surprise
when I surprising signals are generated
by things like me mainly you is to
ensure that I am as much like you as
possible so that I can predict what
you're going to do next because that's
what I was going to do next and exactly
symmetric is so for you so that
basically means that we come to share a
generative model a shared narrative
we're seeing from the same film sheet
and everything becomes mutually
predictable what it doesn't describe
though is the is the uh go back to your
firelight Zone and the the man in the
nice hell the epistemic hell so if it
was the case that we could become
completely mutually predictable I just
keep on singing the same song together
for hour after hour after hour that will
become boring and at this point I think
you're now into sort of social
neuroscience and Joint free energy
minimization
um but you know can sometimes lead to
quite paradoxical uh you know results or
understandings of the way that we
um search for information or engage with
on the one hand I want to be make my
world as predictable as possible so I
don't get any nasty surprises so I'm
going to go to those kinds of news
channels I've talked to this kind of
person because I think that you know we
have a line frame of reference we have
common grounds we speak the same
language
on the other hand I'm going to be
compelled but slightly curious about
other ways of thinking and it's not you
know we're not all going to merge into
one massive community and we are one
massive hive mind one massive collective
intelligence it's that's not going to
work because we are compelled to you
know what would have developed it this
way or what's that kind of person like
what's this culture like uh so yeah I
haven't got the answers but there's a
real you know really really interesting
information in the in the in sort of
social Neuroscience Professor Carl
friston is a world-renowned
neuroscientist and researcher he is best
known for his work in developing
groundbreaking statistical methods and
mathematical models to understand the
workings of the brain and how it gives
rise to complex behaviors our discussion
mainly tackles his free energy principle
which states that the brain is
constantly working to minimize the
amount of free energy in its system
according to this principle the brain is
a predictive engine that is constantly
trying to make script predictions about
the world in order to minimize its own
uncertainty if you got this far Please
Subscribe and I hope you enjoy our
conversation Professor friston thank you
for coming on thank you for inviting me
yes it is a pleasure
um for the folks watching this uh on
YouTube I just want to say they should
know that you are one of the most
sighted scientists in the world and have
made you know Monumental impacts on the
field of Neuroscience so it is the
highest honor honestly to be speaking to
be speaking with you today and thank you
so much for coming on
it's very gracious for you thank you
yeah and um you know your time is very
valuable so I do want to jump right into
it and as we discussed over email the
primary focus of the conversation will
be on your free energy principle
so I think it'd be awesome as as its
Discoverer
um let's maybe set the table so to speak
could you provide a high level sort of
simple description of the free energy
principle and then I have a number of
specifics to ask you about it
right so when confronted with that
challenge I normally say there are two
ways you I know
the description uh so there's a sort of
um intuitive low road approach
um which I'll describe first and then
there's the appreciation of the
principle from the through the lens of a
physicist to try and understand
self-organization but from the point of
view of um
a psychologist or a a neuroscientist
we're talking about a very long-standing
and a way of formulating our capacity to
make sense of our world in terms of
being able to predict so these ideas go
all the way back to Plato and
um
probably kantian in nature but probably
best articulated by helenholtz in in the
19th century that in the sense that
perception is a constructive act it is
um in the words of people like Richard
Gregory it is the brain actively
constructing explanations hypotheses
fantasies for what might have caused my
Sensations so this is a very much as
Andy Clark would say an inside out
process that you're creating a fantasy
um an explanation for what I would have
seen if this was the right explanation
and then you're using the actual
Sensations to correct update and revise
your internal hypothesis your internal
fantasies so on that view you could
regard the brain as literally a
fantastic all then it's a you're a
purveyor of fantasies that are trying to
make sense of of the lived world or at
least the sensed World
um and if you cast that in terms of
inference mathematically
um abductive reasoning and write down
the rules that would have to obtain
um if we were in the game of inferring
the causes of our Sensations then you
get to a formalism that can described in
terms of optimizing a quantity called
variational free energy and this
quantity is quite ubiquitous and
statistics and machine learning
um also known as an Evidence lower bound
and it simply scores the surprise that
is inherent in any sensory evidence or
any sensation and we use that surprise
if you like to revise our beliefs and
that mathematically can be written down
as minimizing free energy so all that
you can think of in terms of what
constitutes a good brain and possibly a
good mind can thereby be described as
Trying to minimize free energy or
minimizing surprise
um you can understand that in terms of
the average surprise which would be
uncertainty so all that this is really
saying it's a mathematical statement
that self-organizing sentient systems
look as if they are trying to minimize
uncertainty trying to find the most
um the best guess if you like the best
hypothesis for the causes of their
sensation you can understand this in a
very generalized sense
um you know you don't have to think of
it in terms of sentence you could
understand this is just a kind of
homeostasis you know both your body and
my body is in the same game of Trying to
minimize surprising deviations from
states of being and we do so
um certainly on the level of physiology
by trying to keep ourselves Within prior
uh prior
ranges of States a temperature or blood
sugar and the like that would be very
surprising if we found ourselves outside
those regimes either very very cold or
um and some kind of physical extremists
so that would be if you like a sort of
biological perspective on the free
energy the physicist would come along
and say
um okay there are certain or possibly
quite remarkable systems in my universe
that seem to
um restrict themselves to certain
characteristic states of being
um they have a peculiar capacity to
resist
the second law of Thermodynamics which I
should say just applies to some closed
systems but
um you know I think it's used for a
useful concept here in relation to this
notion of homeostasis so what
characteristics must these systems
possess in order to keep themselves
within characteristic States technically
you know mathematically of course a
pullback contractor these are just
states of being that look as if they're
attracting certain systems so that they
gather themselves up and keep themselves
Within These characteristic States and
it turns out if you write down
um the equations for the Dynamics of
these kinds of systems then you can
explain or even describe these in terms
of a variational principle of least
action that just says you're always
trying to flow down gradients
established by these surprises these
prediction errors that's as Quantified
by the free energy and that's a really
nice oh that has a very nice
interpretation
because mathematically this surprise is
the negative of what statisticians would
call log evidence
um it is a quantity that measures the
goodness of your model or the negative
of this goodness of your model which is
just simply the probability of my
Sensations
given a model of how I think those
Sensations were generated so this is
exactly the same kind of generative
model you'd find in generative AI or you
know say large language models and the
like
um
so that that
sort of gives you a theological gloss on
this free energy minimizing process
that's just a way of describing
self-organizing systems that have this
particular capacity to uh organize
themselves and resist this entropic
dissipation or dissolution Decay and
death
um and you can describe this as
effectively looking as if they're trying
to maximize the evidence for their
models of the world
so this um and I had to be read as
basically Gathering evidence for my own
existence if I am a model of my lived
world
also in Philosophy by um uh nicely
denoted self-evidencing so it's a
special kind of self-organization that
can be read as self-evidising in the
sense of gathering evidence from the way
I think my world works and how I operate
within that world
so those would be two sort of uh
perspectives on on the same phenomenon
yeah it's wonderful thank you that's a
great summation and the um we're gonna
dive into this and many different we're
gonna cut it we're gonna slice this up
in my different ways but one thing I
haven't heard and I've listened to many
of your um
you know podcast interviews and watch
some of your presentations and read your
papers but I haven't heard yet is what
is the origin story of the free energy
principle you know how did this all come
together for you I know you have a long
history
um in the in the field but was there uh
an aha moment or your Eureka moment some
at some point when did this kind of all
start to um come together what was the
origin of this idea
um well I think the first thing to say
in response to that question is that
this idea has been around for you know
if not Millennials certainly centuries
um and has been
um increasingly formalized and and
simplified so there could be many
starting points to this story and each
will have their precedence so this is a
legacy
um and a legacy of what well you could
argue it's a legacy of
um ideas proposed by Helen Hilton
refined by psychologists Like Richard
Gregory
um Notions of analysis by synthesis and
all sorts of
um you know the brain as a constructive
organ statistical organ trying to make a
sense of its world that you'll find in
the 20th century ideas which were taken
up to great effect in machine learning
by people like Jeffrey Hendon and Peter
Diane they actually invented a helmhels
machine
you know that had this sort of
um this Bayesian mechanics under the
hood borrowing from another other
Legacy left by Richard Feynman which was
you know the the technical resolving the
technical differences of doing this kind
of uh this kind of inference hence the
variation of free energy that he brought
to the table
um in the context of quantum
electrodynamics
um personally
um it all started to make a lot more
sense when reading the work of people
like Raj Rayo
um and Donna Ballard
um and that story was a predicted coding
story
um but you know it transpired that this
was just another way of telling the same
story but you you are using a slightly
different rhetoric so the prediction
errors and predictive coding
um just are a measure of free energy
under certain simplifying assumptions
but the key Insight
um you know in the late 90s wasn't
exactly the same objective function it
could be used to describe both
perception and the spirit of predictive
processing as championed by people by
Andy Clark and predictive coding but
also the learning
um the updates that you urge to
connection strengths you know of the
kind that you'd find in in machine
learning but also you'd find in natural
intelligence and experience dependent
necessity in the brain and the um the
thing that I found particularly
intriguing was that if you just not
stood back and I repeat so looked at
this through the lens of a physicist
you could also explain all of action
through minimizing exactly the same
quantity so
um you know bit by bit everything that
needed to be explained sort of fell into
the camp of it's just minimizing free
energy and everywhere you looked
everything could suddenly be very simply
explained in terms of minimizing free
energy attention
um uh and even in the past few years
your natural selection is just another
free energy minimizing process so this
is
um I haven't really answered your
question in this house because there was
no one moment sure every few years I I
certainly get you know a nice aha oh
it's just another instance of minimizing
free energy and then you write a paper
usually you know
um
using numerical simulations and a bit of
analysis to say well look this is
another way of looking at it and it
looks very much like this kind of thing
because it's all
um if you like a reflection of the same
fundamental process of self-organization
can you give us a sense of um
I guess the scope of this discovery so
as far as I understand it it explains
um you know process a dynamic happening
in the brain which is the most complex
object that we know of in the universe
uh what is the simplest scale what is
the smallest
um say dynamic or or thing that would
adhere to this principle
um does that make sense like basically
what does this principle start yeah yeah
no I just wanted to interrupt to
congratulate you on the question because
that's that's the second focus of many
colleagues
um in um very globology and physics so
I'm thinking here people like Mike Levin
and Chris fields and Jim glazebrook um
so that is that that's absolutely key I
think that notion
um does this apply to a particular thing
or does it apply to everything and if it
applies to everything and what scale
does it apply and does it apply at every
scale and the answer should be it's
scale invariant and it applies to
everything literally
um and that sort of
um perspective is being championed um I
repeat by my colleagues Mike German and
and Chris in the context of quantum
information theory on the one side on
the point of view physics but on the
other side
um there's this story which I think is
very nicely articulated by Chris fields
that they're you know
it is time to remove the bright lines
between physics biology and psychology
they're all just the same thing and you
get this notion of basal cognition which
is something I think Mike Levin has
brought to the table that all uh
self-organization can be read as this
kind of basic sentience that's sort of
basal cognition that is just an
infection of of the existence of things
and this may sound a little bit like an
overstatement but um the you know the
interpretation
in terms of or the interpretation of
self-organization and self-evancing is a
relatively straightforward consequence
of the individuation of anything from
the rest of the Universe
um and this separation
um appeals to what is now a little
literature or
um on Markov blankets in this particular
context so the Markov blanket is just a
definition of thing that's where you
start with the notion okay I want to
explain the states of something and then
you ask
um well what's a thing
you have to appeal to scrolling against
formulation of you know the boundaries
can you explain what goes on within the
boundaries of living things and of
course as soon as you say that you
realize it's the boundary that's the
important
um structure that allows you to
individuate something from everything
else or no thing
um
and indeed if you just look then look
back with that
um with that view on what you learned at
school in terms of physics you suddenly
realize how important that boundary is
less than the heat path in physics for
example uh
so wherever you look the the there's
this crucial notion of
um a separation an individuation and
simply by thinking carefully and
articulating formally how you would
Define that boundary
um there is if you like a partial
separation from
states on the inside of something and
states on the outside of something
but there's a two-way traffic across
this blanket or this this um you know
this this boundary this Markov boundary
and this two-way traffic enables you now
to describe the internal Dynamics the
Dynamics on the inside
as holding beliefs about probabilistic
subpersonal beliefs about the outside
and it is that that enables you then to
um assign this free energy functional to
belief structures in the brain and you
can do this for anything you can do this
for a droplet of oil you can do it for a
virus you can do it for a person you can
do it uh in fact I've just signed off on
a wonderful paper
um by um my colleagues uh um and uh and
Lance DeCosta where they've actually
applied it to the biosphere so the same
maths
um unfolds once you've identified the
separation of something for everything
else you just apply this mechanics of
spazing mechanics and
um
and then you can interpret the
self-organization in terms of sense
making and self-evident and you know an
implicit or a description of that sense
making in terms of belief updating by
minimizing the surprise or maximizing
this basic Bayesian model evidence so
um it can be applied to
um single cells or it can be applied to
the biosphere so it should apply to
everything and so that's what Max Fields
would say at what level of analysis when
it comes to your Quantum information
theoretic applications of the violation
yeah it's fascinating the um I'm
familiar with Chris Fields work I've
read some of his research and actually
spoke with Michael Levin a few weeks ago
yeah we actually covered I mean in great
detail
um one of his papers I think it was 2019
paper called the the computational
boundary of the self
I don't know if you happen to see that
but he has this uh this visual of
cognitive light cones sort of the uh the
boundary the assumed boundary of um of
like nested cells let's say all going
all the way down to the cell
um say the cell then you have a second
and then ant colony and it's sort of uh
he brings up just fascinating ideas
around collective intelligence all
intelligence is being Collective and
stuff like that so yeah a little bit
that's those things quite a little bit
familiar with
um so it's great that you call them out
uh can you define one thing it'd be
great to get some definitions down can
you define free energy so I believe in a
thermodynamic sense it's the amount of
um
available energy for a system to do work
is a simple perhaps one of the simpler
definitions for it is that applied in
the same way in your free energy
principle
yeah again an excellent question
um yes and no
um so the you know the functional form
of the variational free energy and
that's why I tend to say the variation
of free energy so that people do not
misinterpret it as a thermodynamic free
energy the functional forms are
identical
um and they inherit from the same kind
of physics and probability
um density Dynamics
um however thermodynamic
um uh free energy is I think a very
particular application of this kind of
mechanics to certain systems
um so it is you know I think
um from the point of view of a year so
somebody is not a physicist I think it's
important to say the variation of free
energy is a an information theoretic
measure it has no commitments to jewels
or Boltzmann's constants or anything of
that nature it's a it's very much like
um a statistical measure like your a
variance or a um an average or an
entropy so the free energy as
a free energy is just defined
effectively in terms of a a relative
entropy or sometimes known as a kale
Divergence and a constraint or a um an
internal energy
um so the variation for energy is
talking about
um probability distributions it's
talking about information and crucially
it's talking about
um information about things and then we
come back to the the you know the
central foundationals of the Markov
blanket and separating the inside from
the outside so the whole point of the
three energy principle is that you can
interpret the inside States as bowling
information or probabilistic beliefs
about outside States so this is if you
like something quite fundamentally
different from social Channel
information on the surprise of finding
the brain in this state so the brain
will have two kinds of
um free energy it'll have a variational
free energy
which is a comment about its goodness of
fit or its beliefs about what's going on
outside which a statistician would
understand but it will also have a
thermodynamic free energy in terms of
um the actual metabolism and
electrochemical signaling and and the
metabolic states of of uh of the world
that requires a further commitment to um
I repeat sort of interpreting
um
certain quantities
um you know say the amplitude of random
fluctuations in terms of thermal
construct and applying things like
Boltzmann's constant to it so there is a
difference you know there are
um between the two having said that I
think that difference is specious on two
counts first of all
um you know taking a again a fireman s
uh point of view information is energy
and energy is information and at the
level of the analysis that we're talking
about
um you know a thermodynamic
interpretation is just another
interpretation you don't need to
understand self-organization
um if you wanted to talk to some
physicists in the 19th or 20th century
will be useful but it's not necessary
um actually another the other the other
uh uh point is if you did talk to that
kind of thermodynamic
um person
um then you would find that there is a
um these three energies share the same
minimum
um they um
there is a necessary thermodynamic cost
to any variational free energy
minimization or believer dating via
things like that was principle so there
is a physics which really binds these
these two things together
the final point of contact
UM or perhaps the final
um you know some of your more technical
viewers
um the free energy principle that we're
talking about can be regarded as dual to
James's maximum entropy principle
so
um James's maximum entry principle
um basically said that
um the universe or anything in the in
the game of measuring anything else
um will
um
will conform to the principle of a
maximum entropy under constraints and
those constraints are what are supplied
by the generative model that generates
the predictions that are necessary to
provide the surprise so the surprise
part the internal energy part of the
free energy principle is that which
rests upon or is defined in terms of our
world models our our gerited models so
we come back to this notion the what is
the fun what is the reality well it's an
internal energy minus an entropy
um so we want to minimize your energy
you're going to maximize your entropy
and Accord we change its maximum entry
principle but under constraints that
you're trying to minimize internal
energy and that internal energy just is
a surprise that we were talking about uh
who we were talking about before
um so on that view I think there's a
your deep connection between uh a
certain kind of free energy in physics
but it would have to be a genesian the
free energy even with the kind of
strategy he did at school when he
boiling water at night sure yes okay
it's so interesting and actually the the
you bring up William James's Maxim entry
entropy principle something that I
learned about listening to one of your
lectures because I believe you said
I think it's a quote if I have no
preferences at all then my best bet is
to keep options open
so it's a bit of a size as that's like
the non-technical kind of Layman's way
to look at it
um which I hadn't thought of before and
I was actually thinking and it's one of
the questions that I
um
that I have for you and it's something
that I think is really interesting about
this principle is that
um please correct me if I'm wrong or you
know fill in here the preferences are
are built into the Bayesian beliefs is
that correct
yes you you well you you've immediately
gone into
um a much more glorious world of
preferences and purpose and plans and
intentions yeah you know sorry we can go
there later if you want because I it's
no no no no it's a great place to be but
just uh yeah at the moment we've just
been talking about self-organization
surpriseation self-evidencing but and
what you what you've done is is really
speak to
um the active part of this
um so you're just a set of scene
um when you look at particular certain
kinds of systems and specifically
systems that have very precise internal
Dynamics so the random fluctuations are
suppressed or at least at the scale of
observation that you might want to apply
either all the random fluctuations are
ambitioned away but these kinds of
systems basically systems like you and
me
um but not
um systems that are very very small and
very very hot thermodynamically that
would have lots of random fluctuations
but if you can get a big enough system
like you and me
um then it is the case that the solution
uh or
um the variational principles that uh
have to be in play in order for this
um this separation to persist
um the separation of self from non-self
uh to be in pain
um and you apply it to the way that you
act upon the world then it looks then
you can describe this in terms of
minimizing
um the free energy that you would expect
if you pursued this course of action and
it's at that point I think you get
Notions of preferences and um all the
how you could interpret this expected
surprise and you know very much as we've
said before
um one way of reading expected surprise
guess is you know in terms of entropy
um but there's another way of avoiding
surprises which is just to avoid
surprising outcomes which means
complying with the constraints that you
know they were implicit in Genesis
constrained maximum entry principle
the complement of avoiding surprising
outcomes is that it looks as if I am
always acting in a way that
um invinces preferred outcomes outcomes
that just are the characteristic states
that Define the kind of states that
you'd find me in so I think you're
absolutely right that you you know these
prior preferences are just a way of
articulating the typical or
characteristic states that Define who I
am so you can either sort of
um
put a teleology on that and say oh this
thing is behaving as if it prefers to be
in these states it's actively choosing
these courses of action these paths uh
into the future
that result that there's consequences
are that you end up in your preferred
States
the physicist point of view
you put it you you turn that on instead
you start off with a system that seems
to be able to occupy these preferred
characteristic States and then you work
out what Dynamics must these systems
have so you know that's the deflationary
part of the free energy principle you
know it's just a description of things
that have preferred States effectively
and these preferred states are literally
the attracting set that constitutes the
pullback attractor that was mentioned
before so you're absolutely right uh in
one sense that these these preferences
are part of Bayesian beliefs but that
does if you like
um commit you to a rather technological
interpretation of the energy principle
you don't have to do that you can do
that you don't have to do
and please forgive my ignorance yeah
because I might uh I might be uh showing
my hand a little bit here but is the
brain trying to minimize free energy
because it's trying to use as much of it
as possible I know it's trying to
minimize surprise and minimize
uncertainty but like I imagine something
like a resourceful greedy brain
um so is
is the minimization of free energy
um
sort of like the byproduct is this a
downstream effect or is it
the the the the real pump that's that's
moving the water along
does that make sense it makes sense
it's exactly the question which
um I I try to intubate there there are
two completely contradictory answers to
so if you're talking to a physicist
but no no no no no there's no sort of
and there's no there's no aspirations to
uh deploy my free energy in the most
efficient way it's just that's what
systems do systems just settle down to a
free energy minimum that you know well
let's put this another way those systems
that settle down to an attractive set
into a free energy minimum that that is
their definitional attributes and
stiffly that is what things are
um so it is no surprise that it when
um describe when you describe their
Dynamics
um they'll look as if they're trying to
minimize their free energy because
that's what defines them but if you now
talk to a biologist
um or a psychologist then your
description is perfectly out yeah it
will look as if these systems and
particularly sort of uh um systems like
you and me
um are actively Trying to minimize a
surprise and
um you know in a resourceful way
um I I would actually frame that more in
terms of
um in a very efficient way
um so you know you know if you go to
Wikipedia and you say well free energy
is the amount of work available
to do work I mean that that's a
thermodynamic interpretation and you
know
I don't think it's quite necessary to to
put that you know that's out of
authorized things
um but it certainly I think would be
would be
um
you'll be perfectly licensed just to
interpret
um various parts of or decompose
variation of free energy and as for what
would it what would it look like if we
just focused on this particular part or
that particular part
and I think one really interesting
decomposition
of um variational free energy is that
with a statistician would usually appeal
to and that's basically
um accuracy minus complexity where
accuracy is effectively
um how accurate your addictions of the
world are how good is your explanation
on these sensory data or if you're a you
know a statistician sort of you know
empirical data that they're trying to
make sense of
the other thing the complexity I think
is is even more interesting
um so in the same way you were talking
about before keeping your options open
and maximizing your entropy in a quarter
of a change this maximum entry principle
um the same sort of occams like
principle
um emerges in terms of this kind of
complexity term so the complexity is
just a way of lumping Together part of
the internal energy with the entropy to
give you this relative entropy or this
Chao Divergence and to put this very
simply what it measures
is effectively the degree to which some
sensory data or some Sensations or some
sensory evidence changes your mind
so if you're trying to describe this as
a statistician this is the degree to
which you move from your state of
primarilies to your state of posterior
beliefs so it's degrees of freedom
you're using up in terms of providing an
accurate account of your data and it is
this that is minimized remember
pre-energy equals accuracy minus
complexity so I'll actually the other
way around negative three energy is
equal to uh accuracy minus complexity so
as you're minimizing the free energy
you're also you're trying to maximize
the accuracy but at the same time you're
minimizing the complexity so this is
where I think you get what you what you
were alluding to you're trying to
accurately navigate the world
in the most efficient way possible using
up the least resources so why do I say
resolve as well because of this
um link between the information and
energy you're afforded by things like
the jinski equality and the endows
principle it costs energy to change your
mind it costs energy to create and well
to destroy information so that
complexity is also a cost technically
it's also an information game and it's
also
um a complexity cost so what it looks as
if a brain of this kind would be in the
game of updating itself changing its
biophysical state
in a way to make predictions that are
that as accurate as possible whilst at
the same time complying with complexity
constraints so doing them as
parsimonious way uh that it can so hence
Occam's principle
um so that would also translate into
um the most energetically efficient way
of making sense of the world
um and um you know if you sort of um
that in support
um in terms of computation in Silicon
then what you know what that tells you
is that the good computers
um are those computers that work on the
edge very cheaply with small amounts of
electricity they're doing it very in the
simplest way possible and be a with a
cool head literally so I you know these
these These are really interpretations
of if you like unpacking the terms that
go into a variation of free energy and
making sense of them and I think it's a
I think that's exactly what should be
done it's a wonderful game um and you
could also repeat that game in terms of
the expected free energy so now you have
expected accuracy and expected
complexity and when you look at the
functional forms of these terms you
suddenly see things that people have
been dealing with and optimizing or
nearly a century so for example the
expected accuracy
um for the negative expected accuracy is
just the ambiguity or the um the um the
negative Precision
um that would be used to explain an
efficient sampling of the world of the
kind that you might find in the say the
visual cortex of the organization and
the visual brain
the expected complexity becomes risk of
the kind you'd find in economics it is
basically
um the um the distance I move from my
prior beliefs if I pursue this course of
action and of course we've just said
that the pride beliefs about the
consequences of action are our
preferences now describe our attracting
set or our preferred States so now the
expected complexity the risk is just
scoring the degree to which I expect to
be displaced from my third states of
being probabilistically speaking let me
just measure that with the cow
Divergence on the relative entropy so
that's you know that's
um bread and butter for for many
economists another way of um you feel
like I'm packing or rearranging the
terms in terms um
is in terms of
um the the
what is referred to as expected
Information Gain and expected cost so
um those two
um components are exactly those things
you find in in the two aspects of being
base optimal so there are two ways of
being base optimal one way is to
um
minimize your expected cost or maximize
your expected utility or valuable log
preferences and that's the kind of beta
part you'd find in Bayesian decisions
Theory and you can look at that as grab
fathering things like reinforcement and
learning and utility Theory
um on the other hand though you've got
this sort of again this sort of uh it's
not ambiguity it's ambiguity with bells
on which is the expected information
game and that was exactly the objective
function
um devised at the Inception of the
principles of Optum Bayesian design so
if you have the problem of designing an
experiment that's going to yield some
data
uh and you now ask yourself the question
what's the best kind of experiment I
could possibly design that will give me
the kind of information that's going to
resolve the most uncertainty about my
hypotheses what's going to maximize the
expected Information Gain and it is
exactly that quantity that part that
epistemic value in this
measure the resolution of uncertainty
that defines Bayes optimality in the
context of experimental design that may
seem a little bit sort of unconnected to
you and me in conversational just
walking down the road but of course we
are experi we are actively experimenting
all the time just by looking around you
know the way that we move our eyes
socatically every 250 milliseconds every
little Act of this kind is an experiment
so we come back now to the notion of
Richard Gregory that you know perception
just his hypothesis testing what's the
experimentation it's just palpating the
world in the right kind of of way to get
that kind of information that's going to
resolve the most expected surprise or
the most uncertainty and you can have
that you know at the level of visual
palpation every you know four times a
second or the news channels that you you
you you know you would afford epistemic
trust which is probably quite a hot
issue at the moment
or you know the kind of wicked you know
whether you've got a Wikipedia or
whether yeah what's what's who would you
consult your your
we make choices all the time in terms of
what's the best way to act
um and what are the and you know what
the this notion of expected free energy
brings to the table is that there are
there's the imperative of a dual aspect
it's pragmatic aspect that is
um formerly this expected cost where the
cost of the negative or the surprise in
relation to my preferred states of being
um but also to my mind even more
important is this epistemic part this
sort of expected Information Gain that
actually makes us all little scientists
of one sort of
yeah that's incredible I'm glad I'm
recording this conversation because I'm
gonna have to listen to that a few times
over to fully fold together all the
pieces because there's so much there I
actually found this when I was doing
research on the free energy principle
that I was going off and finding
definitions for things because to bring
it all together is
um well it's amazing that it
incorporates so many different
um ideas from different disciplines I
mean you have your Neuroscience but you
also have information Theory I mean it's
physics you know you have all these
different things that you're pulling
together
um and finding these deep truths that I
think are is fascinating
um because that's exactly what Chris
Fields wants he wants to sort of
specifics psychology biology they're all
the same thing and then again you know
when I was trying to answer your
question when was the aha moment that
really wasn't one but every every few
months you'd say oh that's just one of
those well that so you know to my mind
in a sense
um it is that capacity to accommodate
very gracefully things that definitely
have worked in the past
um that haven't been framed in this sort
of simplifying uh sort of unifying
framework it's that capacity which lends
the free energy principle of a veracity
and a utility that you know it
continually impresses me that when when
you were able to delay something that's
endured for centuries or at least
decades that we all use and work and
that you know intensify understanding
and suddenly it fits in with the free
energy principle that to my mind is
um and you know a reflection of the
utility of the free energy principle but
also interestingly
um it means that the free energy
principle is conforming to itself so if
you remember the whole point of view
engine is running accurate explanations
as simple as possible so it should
provide a simple explanation for
everything that's that's that that's
it's uh if you like
um that's its foundational premise uh
you know
so you shouldn't really be surprised you
can you can do economics and
reinforcement learning yeah whatever
yeah one of your my favorite papers is
yours it's I think it's the 300
principle Made Simple made it simple
simple as possible but no simpler I
think is the title or it's close I'll
link to that in the description for
folks who want to uh to want to read
that um I may have butchered that title
sorry but it's close
it was Einstein's famous quote yes it's
from Einstein yeah and I even found that
I didn't know this but there's a great
little article in Wikipedia called uh
the school the principle of simple
Simplicity
um so there's actually you know people
like Nick chater and colleagues
um have have found this you know this
formalization lock comes principle and
it's not you know I think the 300
principle could also be read as a duel
to that kind of uh that kind of
imperative to find those simple
minimally complex explanation system
yeah
so I'd love to um I'll have to focus
some more time on surprise the idea of
surprise
um it's Central to this Theory and
correct me if I'm wrong so it's we're
trying to minimize surprise or slash
uncertainty right does the system want
zero surprise precisely zero surprise or
that might be I imagine that might be
impossible actually so is it is it
trying to approach zero is that
optimally is that better does that make
sense
it does but again you're you're asking
as a biologist not a physicist
um sorry
[Laughter]
but there is a lovely Paradox here the
notice we've been saying uh um in the
past exchange that we are compelled uh
if we exist as certain kinds of things
that have these very precise internal
Dynamics
um to maximize Information Gain so we
are compelled to seek out Nova novelty
we are compelled and seek out surprising
informative
um uh informative uh outcomes
um which needs to be contrasted with
what you've just brought to the table
which is the you know the underlying the
underlying imperative really is that of
homeostasis uh to minimize surprise so
you've got this interesting um dialectic
here which just falls out of the maths
that in the service of Trying to
minimize my surprise to maintain my
homeostatic to keep myself within these
um Within These attracting sets that
have a low entropy remember that the
entropy is just the average surprise so
if I spend my life minimizing surprise I
am by definition when averaged over time
minimizing my entropy is minimizing this
you know the number of surprising
physiological and mental and emotional
states that that I experience during
that period of time but to do that
have to actually go and minimize uh
maximize my expected information again
so I'm going to look as if I'm actually
very curious
so part of keeping my home keeping
myself
out of unpreferred states and minimizing
the surprise which you can read just
prediction error for example
part of underwriting my capacity to
minimize my prediction error is actually
to go and seek out surprising or
apparently surprising
um outcome so I I will I will be
quintessentially curious I will be
sensation seeking I will be answering to
ask answer it'll look as a I'm going to
want to answer the question what would
happen if I did that
um so
um
we it is you know when you say we all
want to minimize surprise we certainly
want to avoid surprising Sensations yes
um you know nociception the underwrites
are
um you know uh beliefs about being in
pain for example uh being very cold
being very poor being very unloved being
dead you know these are all very
surprising states of being which we will
in the moment avoid but that does not
mean to say that we will not seek out uh
those outcomes that can have that have
information so we're still very very
curious and I I say that at length
because there was an interesting uh
philosophical Paradox called the dart
room Paradox that was brought to the
table around the Inception of the three
energy principle in neural philosophy
um and it went along the following well
perhaps you know this you probably know
the specimen I do do you want to tell
tell your views on you also no I wish I
did I'm sorry I don't know about it
right I mean it's a very common sensical
argument that you know if it's the case
you want to minimize surprise why don't
you just go into a dark room turn off
the lights lie down stay there forever
okay yeah
um that's kind of an idea a question I
had why not just jump off a cliff right
that's you'll know the surprise will be
over and then that'll yeah for extreme
but yes well it's it's interesting that
so so why don't we do that and yet we go
bungee jumping
yeah
I'm not jumping off cliffs and
um bungee jumping uh you know they
should be explainable under the free
energy principle
um and of course as a crucial there's a
crucial difference between the bungee
jump and the and the jumping over a
cliff and look to come back to the dart
room problem
um I repeat it's just the Paradox that
um why don't surprise minimizing
machines or artifacts or systems
um
basically sequester themselves from
um their environment and close their
eyes or turn the lights off and remove
themselves from any particularly
surprising Sensations
and the answer to that well there are a
number of different answers depending
upon um how seriously you take the
question uh well let's say this answer
is well that's exactly what I do every
day when I go to bed uh so it's not
quite that surprising interesting yeah
that's so good to counter yeah uh but uh
but you know ignoring the fact that we
do need some down time and there are
good reasons for that in which come back
to this um separation of free energy
into accuracy and complexity
um but more importantly the first thing
I do when I go into a dark room imagine
that you know Europe there's a
conference and you go back to your hotel
room and the lights don't work in your
hotel room because you can't find the
switch so you know what that tells you
first of all the first thing you do you
and I would do as free energy minimizing
creatures in the future minimizing like
expected for the energy maximizing my
um expression information again it's a
turn on the light yeah that's the first
thing that any you know free energy
minimizing system would do
um which
and the second thing that medical
analogy tells you is that you are going
to um you know if you can't find an idea
you're just going to feel your way
around so again this is expiration this
is curiosity this is
um the coming to the imperative to
resolve uncertainty
um remembering that uncertainty is
average surprise so in resolving
uncertainty you are minimizing your
expected surprise but this is about
um outcomes in the future that are not
yet witnessed so again I think there's a
you know when you
um talk about
um things I do
then you are now talking about the
imperatives that underlie action upon
the world and the consequences that live
in the future and in those instances
it's all about minimizing uncertainty
when you're talking about things
um you know my states of being surprised
it's just a measure of my state of being
it's just the likelihood of these
Devastation given my model uh my
predictions of the sensations at this
point of time point in time so the
fundamentally different ways of using
the notion of surprise
I hope that makes sense it's probably a
little bit over answered I've overshared
haven't I no no it's great that that was
useful I mean it is something that I
think that's why I wanted to
um remain at this on this topic on this
on this level because it is I think the
area where I do it I do still have the
hardest time intuiting the difference
between
um Information Gain and minimizing
surprise like those two things they seem
counter or they seem like you know they
CA you can't have both right
um but I think it's partly perhaps a
problem of language and in terms of like
assigning a positive or negative
negative valence to the term surprise so
something like um like an example so I
was thinking about this
um the other day if if you won the
lottery if you had a winning lottery
ticket right you won a hundred million
dollars
um that's extremely surprising and also
very good right but it seemed to be
counter to minimizing surprise right
um so but I think it's a difference of
scale perhaps like um it's like the
it's the difference between perhaps the
overall model and a particular event
within that model you know you know it
is
perhaps using that example could you
possibly help um
help me into it sort of the difference
and where where these tensions kind of
resolve
um but I think I think you've identified
it well actually it's a wonderful let's
talk about winning the lottery which is
very surprising um yes I love I love to
someday
but also I think just uh you know just
to reiterate what what you've implicitly
just said that yeah the word surprise is
applied to many different
um constructs uh sometimes more
anthropomorphic and sometimes less so
but
um when the surprise is used in the
context of uh the free energy principle
or
um and mathematically it has a very
specific and very deflationary meaning
it's just the negative log probability
of some data given your model of how
those data were caused so it's a measure
of the implausibility of getting these
data
given a particular commitment to how you
think these data were generated so I
repeated probably best thought of as a
predictionary you know
um yeah I've some outcome
um and I had a prediction on that
outcome and the surprises is the measure
of the mismatch or the distinction
discrepancy between my prediction and
what I actually observed
um but this is also known as
um the pry vowel Al an information
Theory uh a term coined by tribus
um more formally more generically it's
also called self-information it's just a
negative log probability of an event
conditioned upon the model or the
context in which that event occurred
um so I I think that's if if I was
talking to you know students of physics
information Theory I wouldn't use the
word surprise I'd use self-information
because immediately they know that they
expect self-information is entropy of a
Shannon of a shell and sword so when I
talk about minimizing self-information
I'm using that as a shorthand that's
saying I'm trying to describe systems
that resist a tendency to
um to um that's dispersion that states
so notice that this is uh again as a
very very confusing again this is um if
you like almost the opposite of James's
maximum entropy principle and there's a
reason for that because what we're
talking about here
are is the entropy the average
self-information or the average surprise
of
um actual outcomes
of real
um deterministic variables that that
constitute
um technically the sensory states of my
Markov blanket the the way that the the
world impresses itself upon me so this
has nothing to do with beliefs or
probability distributions it will
surprise afforded this outcome and I
want to you know being a good homeostat
to use as a real cybernetics notion I'm
going to want to make sure that
everything everything that the world
impresses upon me is within the bounds
or you know that something like me can
take and this is just a statement basis
again
um so that kind of entropy we're trying
to minimize
so remember before we're talking about
James's maximum entry principle but the
entropy was about the beliefs about the
causes it wasn't about the actual
outcomes so this is again if you like um
you know a dialectic or a paradox you
know on the one Handler Trying to
minimize the surprise all the
self-information of my
um
of uh the actual uh outcomes that the
the world impresses upon me but when it
comes to
um the
um the Occam's principle view of free
energy minimization I'm now going to try
to maximize the entropy of my beliefs
about the causes of that so it is
complicated uh you know and perhaps like
one should apologize for that it
yeah
it's the same kind of like dialectic
that you get into if you you know if you
commit to James's maximum entropy
principles the right way of measuring
things and understanding things
then you have to say well hang on a
second I thought the whole point of
biological self-organization was to
resist the natural tendency to an
increase in uh entropy I thought the
whole point of Schrodinger's formulation
of life was to minimize entropy so who's
right Schrodinger or James well they're
both right it's just that the entropy of
the things I talk about are completely
different oh sure yeah yeah James and
and and the three energy principle are
talking about
um the entropy of measurements and
beliefs Schrodinger and homeostasis
um and uh synergetics for example
um uh are are talking about the entropy
of outcomes of of measurements of sorry
of the data upon that you use to to
um to make your inferences and build
your beliefs and update your beliefs so
that you know it's a fascinating sort of
Yin Yang and it really forces you to
think about the nature of
these mathematical descriptions and to
what they pertain so you know things
like entropy and surprisal and
self-information are just attributes of
probability distributions so you have to
say of what is it the outcomes or is it
your beliefs about things and with that
sort of in mind you know winning the
lottery is that surprising well if you
imagine it the probability of it
happening to you being surprising I can
see that you might think oh that's
highly implausible so it's not um it's
not uh it's it it is very surprising on
the other hand if you believe that you
are the kind of Lucky child that good
things happen to him and which you have
to believe in order to actually
um self-evidence your way and particular
way into being a happy Chap and the good
things happen to you winning the lottery
is not that surprising that's the kind
of thing that happens to people like me
I'm a successful New Yorker and you know
I wouldn't be that surprised because
that's consistent it's ego syntonic it's
yeah winning the lottery is not going to
put me in a a truly surprising state
that if I had a car accident or I had a
stroke or um you know my partner left me
you know these are truly surprising
things whatever Lottery is not
surprising because it doesn't take me
out of my comfort zone my attracting set
or my pullback attractor furthermore uh
you know well I'm not sure that this
example works so well in practice but
um certainly
um you can now if you um win the lottery
if you did actually win the lottery that
um actually reduces a lot of surprise uh
in terms of what you're going to do next
um so that puts in a certain position
with a certain latitude of ways forward
and ways and ways of Behaving which
actually resolves uncertainty about
um you know whether you're going to be
able to pay these bills whether you're
going to be able to support an elderly
relative whether you're going to be able
to pay for your children to go to
college all of these uncertainties are
exactly what you're trying to actively
resolve but if you're very rich
a lot of those that searches resolve
themselves so that kind of if you like
expected surprise which is all about the
surprise that in terms of things I'm
going to do is actually resolve my
winning lottery so winning lottery is
both good
at that simple level of analysis I'm
sure if you actually speak to people
actually won the lottery you've probably
been a very different different
impression but at least at least at this
level of analysis it's both good and
surprise minimizing
um
yeah right it depends on the frame
almost the frame of reference like which
what state are you looking at it at are
you familiar
um this came to mind the other day as I
was thinking about this principle
um do you ever watch the Twilight Zone
yes from back in the day there's an
episode
um
called a nice place to visit and spoiler
alert for anyone watching but you know
it's an old show so if you haven't seen
it by now but basically in the episode a
thief a robber dies and goes to heaven
and um they're a gambler they like to
gamble so in a casino
uh basically the way it works is they
win every game at the casino they're
playing craps or playing Blackjack and
every time they win right and the robber
is happy you know he's like oh my God
this is amazing everything I play is
it's so great and then
please stop me if you if you've seen
this episode already but for folks
watching
um he's happy at first but then it goes
a month later and he's sitting at the
table and he's bored out of his mind
right he's winning every time and he's
just like ah I won again like oh
who why even play right and it made me
think about this I mean maybe this is
completely off but in the fact that
there's no more surprise in the games
that he's playing right so he's lost all
of the will basically to go on and of
course at the end you find out he's not
in heaven he's in hell right he's got
everything that he wanted but it wasn't
it wasn't the right thing that he wanted
sort of you know the lesson the story I
guess but uh maybe think about this a
little bit because
it basically the surprise is zero and
actually all the valence it's it's only
a negative outcome really for for him
you know he hasn't he hasn't realized
that um the Folly of his actions you
know there's no more hypothesis testing
happening here every every time it's the
same thing and what a dull life to live
it made me think about this a little bit
and please tell me if that's anywhere
close to put this idea I know it's art I
know it's different it's television but
no I think that's spot on I I hadn't
seen that episode that's a marvelous
moral story I know you're absolutely
right so that this is um you know
not only do you see this
um in in Psychology but when you start
to simulate
um you know little animals minimizing
the fearity you see exactly this kind of
behavior and as you say it's just the
fact that the expected surprise
um entails
um
the motivation to
do those things that resolve uncertainty
you know and if you're denied the
opportunity because there is no more
uncertainty to resolve there's no more
curiosity out there there's no more
epistemic avoidance there's no more
expected Information Gain that you
expect because you know everything and
it just keeps happening the same again
and again and again and again that would
be awful
um you know
um and you know when you actually
simulate it
um you you actually can simulate little
artifacts who just get so bored they do
nothing
um and essentially they have you know
once they attain their preferred States
they're maximized their expected utility
or minimize their um expected cost
because there's nothing to shape their
behavior because there's no no reducible
uncertainty out there there's no more
um there's no more epistemic affordance
there's nothing to do uh and you know
they just sit there and do absolutely
nothing and that must be an awful
situation to be in uh and I say that
because you know 99 of your life is not
chasing
um you know if you were a mouse cheese
it's not putting yourself in a position
where you're going to win the lottery
it's actually indulging in your
curiosity the very Factor you're doing
these
um these podcasts
um
having this exchange is just an
expression of the fact you are compelled
to be a curious creature though this is
part of our makeup and if we didn't do
this then you know at least from a
mathematical perspective it's highly
unlikely that we would exist over
um you know over you know an appreciable
period of time so yes I hadn't I hadn't
seen that episode but you know I love
the twist that you end up in and end up
with hell yeah yeah that's bad well he
was a thief so he deserved it uh
I do have so about the um
let's see here I'm trying to figure out
where we're gonna go the I believe
there's two ways right to minimize
prediction error
um they were change the model to better
fit sensory input and or change the
world act on the world in order to
better fit the prediction but I wasn't
sure are these two mutually exclusive I
mean do you have to choose between the
two and if so how does the system decide
which one to do
right so um we're now at a sort of um
more Elemental uh application the 300
principle just to understand
um the fundamental the you know the
fundamental drives to both perception
and action and you've you face up
beautifully but so you know if we now
um simplify things and then just read
surprise and free energy in the moment
as prediction error then there are two
ways as you say that I can minimize my
prediction or I can either change my
mind so my prediction error has become
more like the sensory data at hand or I
can act upon the world to solicit some
more or a different set of sensory input
that are closer to my predictions so
what would that look like and what it
would look as if um I am basically
acting to fulfill my predictions which
is what I meant before so if you weren't
optimistic uh your successful New Yorker
um you know if you didn't have that
prior that optimism that sort of um
um optimism bias that you know
um then you you wouldn't be able to act
in a base optional way because you need
to fulfill your own predictions to
survive the you know you know there's
something quite fundamental about that
but
at the level I think we're talking
um the kind of self-fulfilling
prophecies we're talking about are very
sub-personal so all we're talking about
basically is uh effectively reflexes so
you know when we when we move when we
talk or move our eyes what's happening
is that we
um we're sending predictions down to uh
the ponti nuclear to the spinal cord
about the kind of signals we're getting
from the state of our body uh
technically it's called proprioception
and if I predict that I'm going to be
moving in a particular way I would
expect to get these signals from my
muscles
and if I don't get them there's a
prediction error so by acting all I mean
or all that one means in the setting is
that you send these prediction errors
back to the muscle so that it contracts
to the right length so it sends the
signals that you predicted so this is
just like a thermostat it's just like
um
feedback control that we find you know
in in many many devices all you need to
supply is a set point the temperature
you want or the stress the length of the
muscle you predict will happen and then
the body does the rest so this is how a
very sort of Elemental level of just
moving around
um the
um you can understand Action Motor
Action Motor being the use of particular
kinds of muscles uh as minimizing
prediction error or minimizing free
energy so it's not quite what you know
there's more if uh deliberative uh
planned kind of action you know it's not
how do I imagine myself behaving
tomorrow or generally
um unfolding this conversation we're
talking about action in the moment uh as
basically eliminating prediction errors
reflexive very very very quickly so an
answer to your question how do we decide
which to do and are they um are they
um mutually exclusive they're certainly
not mutually exclusive in the sense that
the whole point of
um this explanation of action and
perception and the action perception
cycle is that they there is a a common
theme it's just all driven by minimizing
prediction error uh or minimizing free
energy in a more job context
um
however in practice I think you're
absolutely right that we we do seem to
be built to
um switch between the two so in
principle you could do them both at the
same time in principle you could
dynamically adjust your set points and
you your uh your reflexes could try and
fulfill those set points or those
predictions uh and the two could go hand
in hand and temporaneously but in fact
in practice it looks as if the the
there's actually a term taking
um and it looks as if um certainly sort
of larger mammals
um have a very particular schedule of
turn taking uh I mean this space sound
very specific but I think it's really
interesting that yeah and it speaks to
the cognitive moment
um so it looks as if if we just take say
vision
then um our vision it's only Active
Vision
um where
sometimes described as active sensing
um where we actually have to go and
palpate
and select little parts of the visual
scene bearing in mind we can only
actually see a very very small part of
the visual scene without you know with
high resolution enough for real
representations so basically
um although we think we can see
everything we're not we've just seen
little patches and we're knitting it
together in our heads it's fantasy that
I can see everything that's not true you
could see something if you looked over
there and that gives you the illusion
that you can see everything in fact you
can't uh so this is part of the sort of
the bread is a fantastic organ having
the fantasy it can see all around me uh
you can't you have to go and get very
the most
um
epistemically Rich expected to maximize
the expected Information Gain
um parts of the visual field to knit
together and to accumulate the right
kind of um the right kind of information
that builds your hypothesis about what
the scene that I'm currently
constructing in my head and this process
happens very very quickly so remove our
eyes about four times a second
okay yeah interestingly well yeah it is
amazing but it's also well I find even
more amazing is that everything seems to
be about four times a second and by
everything I made if you're a mouse you
wouldn't really be using your eyes so
much you'd be using your whiskers as you
go around your different Burrows or
you're in the field and you whisk about
four times a second
if you are talking you produce little
chunks of information called phonemes
about four times per second when you're
listening you're listening at about four
times per second when you sniff
you slip it about four times per second
so in the way that we sample the way
that we sort of
um uh gather our information from the
world
seems to have this very saltatory aspect
that you're roughly up four Hertz yeah
technically a Theta Rhythm we seem to be
going to sampling the information but
what even more interestingly
during the action during the actual
movement itself
the way that you adjudicate between
changing your mind and updating your
your allowing your brain to
um revise its beliefs by changing its
neural activity to provide better
predictions
um during movement
um you actually attenuate the
consequences of that movement to enable
you to act so this is a really
interesting phenomena called sensory
attenuation
um but simply you know if I had the
um the prior belief that I was going to
lift my arm
and I didn't ignore or attenuate the
prediction errors that were coming from
my arm telling me my arm is not moving
then I wouldn't be able to lift my arm
because those predictionaries would come
and revise my beliefs no no my arm's not
moving but if I can ignore the
sensations that I am going to generate
then I can use my reflexes to fulfill my
predictions that my arm is actually
raising so in order to move I have to
attenuate the prediction errors that are
if you like undermining my predictions
and this is called sensory tenuation and
it's beautifully exemplified in eye
movements so yo if you if you now you
know look at this finger and then it's
the card to this finger
yeah
whilst you were moving circading and
moving your eyes from one finger to the
other finger
you were suppressing and attenuating all
the prediction errors and I know that
because you didn't see the massive optic
flow the shift of the world induced by
moving your eyes you can actually see it
if you press your eye this is how the
horse's uh
um famous experiment if you just gently
nudged the outer edge of your eye you'll
see the world shift around
huh
I don't want to push it too hard I'm
like like careful to the viewers at home
don't poke your eye out uh but okay
just jump around a little bit it does
yeah so
um that's because your eyes weren't
causing the motion
um and you were able to actually
register and attend to that visual that
visual motion that visual if you like
retinal slip
exactly the same signals were being
generated when you were moving your eyes
with your eye muscles and you didn't see
that you didn't see the world jump right
all you saw was my finger and then my
finger again in a different position the
world had not moved so you were actually
attenuating your sensory prediction as
your visual prediction errors during the
movement
uh that's called psychotic suppression
and it's a remarkable capacity of the
brain to temporarily suspend attention
to self the consequences of
self-generated
um
Sensations and this happens everywhere
It's a Wonderful explanation for
um uh the phenomena
when you know you've got two children in
the back of the car and he hit me hard
and I hit him and you know the
escalation in the argument absolutely
right because when they're hitting they
attenuate the uh sensory information
from the reports how hard they're
hitting
so they actually feel being hit as as
more intense than they feel they're
hitting so they just they're just like a
little arms race let's ratchet up and
this is due to sensory generation you
could actually use that metaphor for a
lot of political a political exchange is
that is that related to I know if you've
ever heard this I actually don't know if
it's technically true I think it is I've
tested it out I've asked people to test
this out how you can't tickle yourself
yep yep the same kind of exercise that's
a great observation so in fact that
example comes from people like Daniel
walpert who I think is now actually in
New York
um and Sarah Jane Blakemore um and uh
you know trying to understand the the
remarkable
um first of all why is it you know it is
remarkable you can't particular yourself
because you're attenuating the
consequences of self-generated behavior
so in a sense you know the fact you
can't induce visual motion by moving
your own eye with your eye muscles is an
example of that but you can circumvent
that by tickling your eye tickling your
eye by using something you're not used
to which is which is your finger so that
you know that it is exactly that notion
you can't tickle yourself
which explains this sort of uh little
little experiment it actually it divides
by uh by hell health so you can perform
on yourself the interesting thing is
that um what Sarah and colleagues and
Chris frith were pursuing
um and uh super shergill
um was that people with schizophrenia
have great difficulty
um in this kind of sensory attenuation
in another Paradigm called the force
matching Paradigm which
um means that people
um there may be certain
um psychopathologies
um that interfere with your ability to
suspend attention to the consequences of
your own actions so for example if you
had in a speech
uh and you heard yourself because you
were not attenuating the consequences of
your own speech you might then try to
explain away these unattenuated auditory
or pseudo auditory inputs as if somebody
else was speaking and then you had it so
this is the notion that Chris Ritter
brought to the table as an explanation
for auditory hallucinations
if
um you were able to sense your own
movements
um and were not you know if you moved
and you were not able to attenuate
um the sensations of movement
um it might feel as if somebody had
caused your movement so you've got this
phenomena made acts so there are all
sorts of very quite frightening
experiences that would ensue if you
failed to have this sort of turn taking
between action and perception especially
at this very very time scale
um
um and you know some of these
frightening consequences you know one
could argue I've seen quite frequently
in many dices in Psychiatry and indeed
neurology
for example Parkinson's disease
um an abnormality of dopenergic
neurotransformation where dopamine in
this context is thought to affect the
um the capacity to do this the you know
this kind of sensory attenuation at a
particular level in the motor system and
therefore
um subverting Your Capacity to realize
your intentions to move so what would
that look like what it would look like
somebody who can't initiate an act
um and that of course is one of the
common symptoms of Parkinson's disease
so you know this this adjudication
between acting and perceiving sort of
you know quickly going out there moving
actively ignoring the consequences of
that women until you get there and then
fixating not moving getting the
information sorting it out doing your
processing and then starting again the
cycle of action perception where you
have actually got the separation in play
is at least from a biological
perspective you know
um seems to be a sort of ubiquitous way
that we actively sense our world or
actually makes make sense of our world
and can be and is very very Reliant upon
this uh this notion of selective
attention sensory attenuation to get
that that dance between action and
perception
um exactly right
sure that reminds me if I tell you just
a personal anecdote from last summer it
was a random day I was out in my fire
escape eating smoke meal uh and you know
I do this in some days and
all of a sudden there was I live on a
one-way Street
but coming the opposite way was a police
chase there was an s a dark SUV being
chased by a cop car and I remember
the first second or two where I was
looking over at what was happening
I didn't quite see the vehicles
I saw
what can I describe as like a fuzzy
black cloud
it took a second or two for my brain to
catch up to what was happening and to
construct a car
being chased by another car
it was very bizarre because I mean it
was highly unexpected right it just
doesn't happen every day and
um I'm not sure if that's a common thing
with people who see things that are
extremely uncommon but
um I did have that and perhaps as I was
just getting into sort of the perceptual
um science literature and reading about
the stuff so perhaps it's hard it's hard
to disentangle that from expectations
let's say but I mean it really stuck
with me as
you know one confirming although it's
well confirmed obviously in the science
but that this is what our brain is doing
is constructing you know correcting for
errors because that's a you know highly
uncertain or really surprising thing to
happen and my brain in real time took a
second or two to cohere and make that a
make that a solid those solid objects
yes
uh that that's a wonderful story and and
yeah yeah as you say I mean it really
speaks to the you know the brain as a
constructive organ
um as an organ that that really has
tried to actively make sense of what's
going on and sometimes in
um ambiguous situations that can take
many many seconds so you you would also
I think you you may be able to
ReDiscover
um that remarkable
um
if you like suspension of of the fallacy
that we can perceive immediately uh and
sort of see see yourself seeing uh using
things like ambiguous figures so it's
like a physicists have a whole range of
really beautiful experiments you know
using ambiguous figures and different
kinds of illusions that deliberately put
you on the edge so that you're you're
you you you have
um experience the sense making and all
the sort of settling down at one option
or another option you know resolving the
fuzzy Cloud into oh yes that's the
percept that makes the most sense in
this instance
um and sometimes it's you know when
you're looking at ambiguous figures for
example sometimes it stops making sense
and you cannot voluntarily stop yourself
seeing the other interpretation so
you're famous two faces are revolves uh
um example so you know I think these
kinds of experiments that kind of
experience really do speak very
powerfully to
um
the kind of experiments you can do at
home to convince yourself you've got a
very fantastic organ but but it takes
time to construct the fantasies in
situations which you're not used to
um either you'll wait until you
experience a a card a police car chase
or you can go and look at some uh sorry
illusory stimuli devised by by a
psychophysicist I I should just add
though if my um as well colleague Alan
Hobson uh was here he just remind you
that you know
if you want evidence that your brain
constructs all your percepts um just
think about dreaming yeah yeah that is
such clear evidence that we you know our
vision is actually something we build
from the inside and it's just gently
constrained by
um in the form of prediction errors the
actual Sensations uh then just think
about your visual experiences
um you know during
um enjoying dreaming so I want to ask
you about that the while you're dreaming
let's say having a
standard dream I don't know what a
standard dream is but you know that's
like having a typical dream where you're
in it and uh you're not non-lucid let's
say and you're out and you're on the
beach or something
is there
aside and said while you're in the dream
you're experiencing it you're not you're
not realizing it's a dream you're not
realizing that you're constructing the
environment the beach
so is there in a sense a Markov blanket
between
your personal your first person
experience in that dream and the dream
world
or does that make any sense like am I
getting fuzzy here I mean is there
technically is it technically the same
thing or is it different
um I think I think technically it is it
is the same thing
um it's just you know you introduced a
really challenging issue there that you
know do you know that you are dreaming
or not I mean sometimes you you do know
you're feeling it certainly contribute
to into Lucid faces also uh really
working making up so I'm just thinking
um you know a proper answer to your
question would have to accommodate the
fact that you um you perceive and you
act in this world
um and yet you do not you're not aware
that you are um you are actually
dreaming and that musting as you say
induce a whole series of markup and
because first of all you're sequestered
from the sensorium so the you know the
biological state of of dreaming rests
upon a particular kind of sensory
attenuation which is very enduring and
lasts for many hours if you're sleeping
properly but it's mediated by the same
neurochemical the same modulator
neurotransmitters that we were talking
about before relation to Parkinson's
disease different kinds but certainly
you know basically the same kind of
functional role so basically you're
switching off sensory input from the
periphery on the body
um so you're now letting your brain Free
Will in terms of generating predictions
um and um resolving out of uh in a
hierarchical context where you're
resolving the self-generated predictions
by other parts of the brain trying to
explain them away so effectively you're
rehearsing your prior beliefs about the
narratives that you usually
um you know or something constrained by
the experiences you've had the previous
day and yet as you say you're not aware
that you are dreaming so there's
certainly high levels of this
hierarchical construct or uh say deep
levels if we think of a centripetal like
hierarchy or heteraki
um that um that have dissolved that
sense of presence and wealth word or no
sorry that is associated with the
reality monetary uh so yes not only is a
remark of blanket
established and that separated you from
the sensorium but there's possibly
another higher one that separated your
normal
um Reality Checking and self modeling
from certain parts of the brain that are
engaged in rehearsing particular
fantasies that you know are experienced
as dreams one of the things I was
thinking about with your model
um
but the principle is
I understand what the system is doing
um a bit in terms of like having its own
internal States is the environment can
we think of the environment as doing
anything with surprise or are we staying
agnostic on what the environment is
doing
right
um so again
um
a very leading question so I'm sorry
good good
I've just yeah there's a whole other
sort of uh podcast
and possibly I'm not the best person to
have that conversation there are people
who who
speak I think in an informed and very
fluent way about this perspective but
you you what you are suggesting
um is that one can appeal to the
mathematical symmetry of this way of
partitioning the inside and the outside
of the Markov blanket which has a an
exact symmetry so that technically uh
certainly in the at the level of sort of
basic sentence and sense making
um of the kind we were discussing
um earlier on
um it is mathematically true that you
can also you can also interpret the
environment as inferring your internal
States because you've got this
generalized synchrony which is another
manifestation of
um self-informational surprise or
surprise minimization when the surprise
of the measure of your sensory
um the sensory Impressions so on that on
that view
the environment
um now
um
is acted upon by you
um in the way that from the
environment's perspective render your
actions sensory inputs and the way that
the environment acts upon you is by
providing you with physical Impressions
but yes you know mathematically speaking
the environment so it should certainly
be modeling uh you
um and you know there are various
flavors
um of that truism that you could pursue
one would fully acknowledge that there
is clearly a vast asymmetry between you
and your environment the environments
usually making bigger it doesn't always
have the same delicate structures or the
precise mechanics and would require the
sort of planning that we're talking
about in terms of the expected free
energy so we're not saying the
environment brands but in terms of still
trying to minimize prediction errors and
doing the right kind of learning about
you I think there is good evidence well
you can certainly read certain aspects
of the environment as doing exactly that
so the favorite example is the
um the elephant path of Desire path the
shortcut that is worn by repeated use
across a grassy lawn
um when you get into you know want to
cut a corner to walking through the park
or to your favorite
coffee cafe
um so one way of looking at this is this
is something I've done uh or you know to
my environment and I've done it with mic
on specifics and I've created a little
path to uh my favorite face or the race
that is the favorite of me and Michael
specifics from the environment's point
of view it's learn a lot about the
behavior of its inhabitants of its
denisence so you know you think you are
impressing yourself on the environment
the viable points environments point of
view it's just invincing kind of
plasticity an experience dependent kind
of learning where it's remembering
things about you
um and you can take that argument right
through to
um those kinds of parts of the
environment that are actually
constructed by con specifics
um like traffic lights like signs that
have a semiotics and so deontic Valiant
um
so you could just you know you could say
that the the lived environment that you
would Express if you walked out onto the
street it's all man-made and it's all
built to
um uh maximize expected Information Gain
I mean what is a sign it is there to
create an environment that states our
curiosity in terms of making it easy uh
to respond to epistemic affordances that
you're underright are curiosity or
um our plans to maximize expected
information again but we build that so
this then you get into the role of
yourself into the game of cultural Niche
construction and the notion of the
designer environment from Andy park for
example
um so you know all of these you know I'm
just summarizing
conversations you could have probably
with other people they want to the final
kind of conversation you might have is
that when you realize that your
environment
is composed of other things very much
like you right
when you're young your mum or uh as your
older or your colleagues and your
friends and your family and your uh and
your your your uh on specifics on the
street
um and I think that's interesting
because now we get into a much more
symmetrical
um sort of relationship between me and
the environment and certainly in this
context young most of my universe is
basically you and me so now there's
there's a certain kind of symmetry in
play
um whereas you are my environment and I
am your environment and yet we both have
gelatin models of our environments which
basically means I have a change of all
of you and you have a generative model
of me minimizing the surprise in the
exchange is uh one description of
um can be um understood as leading to a
generalized synchrony literally are
meeting their minds a um a mutual
predictability the restful certain
things such as communication and
language and certain common frames of
reference common common ground but you
could actually argue that in this
setting
it is an inevitable consequence of joint
free energy or surprise minimization
um when we put two of the things that
are sufficiently similar together
um that this would be inevitable
um that the best way to minimize
surprise
when I surprisingly signal they're
generated by things like me maybe you is
to ensure that I am as much like you as
possible so that I can predict what
you're going to do now it's because
that's what I was going to do next and
exactly symmetrically so for you so that
basically means that we come to share a
generative model a shared narrative
we're seeing from the same him sheet and
everything becomes mutually predictable
and that would be one explanation for
the kind of in-group formation and the
kind of um
um
you know the mechanisms you might find
in evolutionary psychology and you know
that could be described in terms of
Niche instruction what it doesn't
describe though is the is the uh going
back to your Twilight Zone and the the
man in the nice hell the epistemic hell
so if it was the case that we could
become completely mutually predictable
and just keep on singing the same song
together for hour after hour after hour
that will become boring so now we come
back to
um you know what would this kind of
mechanics and this way of understanding
self-organization look like when I'm
packed in societies and in exchanges
between different kinds of con specifics
and you get into really interesting uh
questions about polarization in group
out group the sphere of ideas and spread
of memes that can be simulated
um you know and at this point I think
you're now into sort of social
neuroscience and Joint free energy
minimization
um
um that you know can sometimes lead to
quite paradoxical uh you know results or
understandings of the way that we
um search for information or engage with
people on the one hand I want to be make
my world as predictable as possible so I
don't get any nasty surprises so I'm
going to go to those kinds of news
channels I've talked to this kind of
person because I think that you know we
have a line frame of reference we have
common grounds we speak the same
language
on the other hand I'm going to be
compelled to be slightly curious about
other ways of thinking
um but it's not you know we're not all
going to merge into one massive
community and you know one massive hive
mind one massive collective intelligence
it's that's not gonna work because we
are compelled to you know what would
have developed it this way or what's
that kind of person like what's this
culture like uh so yeah I haven't got
the answers but there's a real you know
really really interesting information in
the in the in sort of social
Neuroscience sure it reminds me a bit
about
um I think you've spoken to it about
um
the Explorer exploit trade-off
uh eetl a little bit because
it's sort of this the balance between
exploiting sort of the
the nearest
say most accessible forms of energy or
say news news content but then also
having this balance between doing that
and exploring say other modes of thought
or you know um exploring what else is
out there and that balance that getting
that that balance right and I think you
said something to the effect once about
the free energy principle that it gets
was it solves it in the right order
something to that effect
um I think it's and the way I perceived
it was or reviewed it was in order to
know what's surprising how to know
what's possible kind of does that make
any sense is that yes yes
absolutely so yeah I probably said it
sort of dissolves the exploitation
expression dilemma but you're absolutely
right it does so in a particular way
um and it does match on the in terms of
the order in exactly the way you say so
if I put
um if I go to this gambler's heaven
um
uh you know there's an enormous
opportunity for me to resolve
uncertainty and to indulge my curiosity
then you know respond to epistemic
affordances which is the expected
information part of the expected
surprise and the expected free energy
and that's so I'm going to first of all
explore all possibilities what is
possible in this particular new
environment I moved to a new city or
I've got a new uh device in the kitchen
so the first thing I'm going to do is
explore by becoming a little scientist
and trying out this and that and going
there and seeing what happens until I
have resolved sufficient uncertainty
that there's no more you know reducible
uncertainty there and at that point the
component the expected Information Gain
will fall below the expected costs or
the expected utility so I'll have innate
preferences you know um that uh
constantly you know put constraints on
my expiration so
um at the point where you uh you
literally um your epistemic um expected
Information Gain Falls below the
expected
um value then the expected value will
take over and I will switch
deterministically to exploitative
behavior so that means the first thing
I'm going to do is explore and then uh
so that there is no
um uncertainty left to resolve and then
I will exploit so exactly secure the
possibilities and then
um and then just act in a way that is
predominantly dictated by my prior
preferences or my constraints another
way of looking at that is
um
we are primarily
um surprise minimizing
um or uncertainty minimizing creatures
but we do so in the constraints the
constraints are provided by our prior
preferences or by our the
constraints uh afforded by the fact that
our being in this state would be very
very surprising so you know one way of
looking at this sort of resolution of
the exploitation expert expression
dilemma is that it's not a dilemma in
any sense we are quintessentially
exploration machines okay exploration
curious artifacts but we have
constraints that we can't become dead or
disabled or dehydrated or dissipated uh
we can't allow ourselves to to be
damaged
um but under those constraints our
primary you know imperative is to
explore
unless of course there's nothing left to
explore and then we get more
yeah sure
it's the trade-off are you familiar at
all with um
I believe it's it's called a number of
different things but uh it's like a game
theory question so they call like the
marriage problem or the secretary
problem you've ever heard this before
yeah so um would you like to hear it I
don't know but like Yeah so basically
the way the game works is um if you're
looking for you know partner a life
partner and
um
the question is how much how many
partners how many people should you date
before
um settling on one person you know how
do you know uh the available options I
guess how do you know when to stop
looking is kind of the question it's
also called the secretary it could be
called the hiring problem because sort
of like the question of you know you you
see one applicant you have to say yes or
no to that one applicant and if you say
no you you can't go back to them right
um jilted X let's say you know you can't
ever go back to apparently what's
optimal is and you have to know it's
what's interesting is you have to know
kind of how long you're willing to date
you know how many partners are you
willing to sort of uh to suss out and
um
the answer is you you you basically date
and you say no to the first 37
of potential Partners or potential
applicants let's say for a job and then
after that point you say yes to
the first person who's better than all
the options you saw already
it's kind of how it works right so it's
like you have to date around you have to
kind of explore but even if you find
someone that's incredible by this model
you you're not supposed to say yes to
anybody until you've seen a little more
than a third of the whole people that
you're that you're trying to observe and
that just makes you think about eeto a
little bit because
you know requires a certain amount of
exploration obviously there's certain
parameters here that are more firmly set
than you'll find for most system
environment Dynamics but that there is
actually technically a mathematically
precise
sort of strategy that works across the
board so I just thought I'd share that
no I haven't heard that that's that's
brilliant and yeah it reminds me sort of
evolutionary Game Theory having sort of
you know stay win so tit to tap like
different strategies and yeah which
Super things in an evolutionary sense
yeah the free energy principle how it
how it reacts to or how it's related to
the Hamilton's principle of least action
can you possibly make that help um make
that link yeah well um so um the free
energy principle
um as we were discussing in Iran can be
regarded either as a variation principle
of least action or
um a constrained maximum entry principle
is depending upon um you know your your
favorite way of understanding the math
um so the uh the variational principle
of least action just is an instance of
how it's expensive Middle East action
um technically what both when applying
Hamilton's principal at least actions
say to
um mechanics or movement of massive
objects for example what these
principles prescribe as a
um a prescription of the trajectory or
path that something will take so you
could apply
um Hamilton's principle of least action
to the trajectory of a ball if thrown at
a particular angle with a particular
velocity team from this point
um and it would be the case that the
trajectory coursed out by that ball
would be a path of least action it would
be the path that
minimized a certain energy when averaged
along that path so this is a path
um interval between meaning sort of
adding things up so the path of least
action the path of least at least
resistance if you like uh where the
resistance scores the
um the expenditure of energy in order to
you know because it deviated From the
Path
um it is prescribed by the principle of
least action and you can use that
principle then to predict or to describe
the most likely path uh that anything
will take
um and indeed that that sort of path
Interpol view is exactly where free
energy the variational free energy comes
from but here we're talking about sort
of Feynman trying to work out the
probability of various Paths of small
particles or say electrons
um so you know a very difficult
mathematical problem that was finessed
by introducing this notion of a
variational bound on the probability of
a particular path uh in his pathological
formulation Quantum electrodynamics the
math is identical to the free energy
principle and it just says that there is
a particular path
through a space of beliefs that is the
most likely
um and um in the same way that there is
a particular path if I throw a ball that
is conforms to help someone's principle
release faction
um the the the space through which we're
talking about
um perhaps traveling now is the space of
probabilistic beliefs encoded by the
internal states of something so slightly
more abstract it's more about the
measurement thing
um the um the sort of genes in use of
the word entropy or the way that James
would
um apply his entropy to to belief
structures
um but the you know the the mathematics
the variational calculus is exactly the
same it just tells you
given
um a particular initial condition
um uh and um
some sensory input for example I can
tell you the most likely trajectory of
beliefs that would be described in terms
of these Leaf updating for example
um that it will will ensue using this
variational principle of least action
which is the free energy principle it's
exactly the same man
um yeah I'm just trying to think of even
more intuitive ways of um
of describing it yeah it's it's a path
of least that effort it's just a
mathematical way of describing the path
of least
um cut into the future or the past of of
least effort where the effort is
effectively effectively scored by the
amount of surprise I can I I can um I
can avoid
gotcha and are you familiar having to be
familiar with um
Jeremy England's work uh with
dissipative adaptation
yeah yes well I was about four years ago
pre-covered yes I haven't I haven't read
what what he's been up to recently same
movies
oh really oh I didn't realize it moves
yeah yeah
but it's it's far more of it I know it's
more of a thermodynamic it's solely I
think I believe from thermodynamic but
it makes me um
because one of my uh
general interest or one of the things I
try to get to is like just you know
you're taking something at the 300
principle you try to think okay what's
even more fundamental than that right
you can keep trying to cut away and say
okay well how do you make this even
you know what's what's what's what's
behind that what's what's below that
what kind of feeds into that and um
I don't I mean it to be completely
transparent I don't fully understand how
dissipative adaptation works I think has
something to do with uh the environment
uh adjusting itself to
best accept the energy that's flowing
through it some something like that but
of course it's very technical
um is that at least I know it's maybe
been a few years since um you follow the
uh follow the idea but does that does
this conform well I guess it would have
to but uh does this play into the free
energy principle at all or is this a
dynamic that
kind of works
it's fascinating work and you may you
may also want to invite Suzanne still uh
into one of these conversations who's
been doing very similar work um from the
point of view of sort of predictive
information Theory and and recently
she's also been looking at this sort of
uh remarkable capacity of systems
um to uh again resist the second law and
in your your use use their free energy
thermodynamically but she would frame it
in terms of information Theory
um to um if you like extract order from
from chaos
um and you know Common to a lot of these
Notions some notion of a ratchet that
you you know you you you you you you
could make little random jumps that you
you
um you maintain them
um and each jump uh is maintained
um if it's heading in the right
direction uh you know fail minimizing uh
sort of uh free energy offense of
something else however I have to say
it's not really
um addressing the same kinds of issues
that the free energy principle is
addressing I have to say
um also you won't get more fundamental
or simple in the free energy principle
um so I look at thermodynamics as one
particular domain of application of that
kind of mechanics
um the only difference between
thermodynamics and the free energy
principles the free energy principle
actually commits to a thinner so it
commits to a Markov blanket so it's now
got a partition of states where you can
start to talk about beliefs in a
non-trivial sense in the sense that
um there is a
um amorphism from the internal states of
a physical system to the states beyond
the heat path or beyond beyond the
blanket and all the more interesting
questions we have about maintenance of
that blanket or the heat math it's not
about the equilibrium physics of things
on the inside most of feminism just
rather uninteresting descriptions of
ensembles of things on the inside that
have some particular exchangeability
criteria and then you can apply for
classical equilibrium physics to that
that's not terribly interesting from the
point of view of um people looking at
non-equilibrium physics and even less
interesting from the point of view
people looking at the real randomly
dynamical coupled systems because these
systems are not exchangeable you you
mentioned before that Mike Levin's
description of
your cells of cells of cells of cells
and boundaries about as a boundaries and
boundaries Markov blankets and blankets
and blankets and blankets there's a
heterogeneity to implicit in that
scaling variant description of actual
systems that will not allow you I think
to apply to adopt the assumptions that
are that we would have to and commit to
if you wanted to apply thermodynamics so
I I am it's serve attitude to
thermodynamics
um so
um in that sense
um the you know
trying to understand the thermodynamics
of itself organization I think it's
possibly misguided because you have to
make too many commitments to the kind of
systems particularly the exchangeability
of ensembles
to make it really interesting on the
other hand
the the questions that people like
Jeremy England and Suzanne still more
recently have been addressing and I
think deeply interesting uh and I'm not
really impressed by the free energy
principle I think what you're talking
about here is the there's a sort of uh
the complexification
that seems to be an inevitable property
certainly of biotic self-organization
You could argue other kinds of
self-organization and certainly biotics
of organization uh far from equilibrium
systems that have this kind of scale
freeness and implicit heterogeneity in
them
um
you know I think that there has yet to
be
um a simple story to explain why we are
becoming increasingly more sophisticated
increasingly but if we are
um
we're organized uh uh I think that's a
fascinating issue I I don't have a clear
answer you know and I will be
um the free energy principle itself does
not properly address that because the
Friendship principle starts by saying
let's assume something as self-organized
it's uh has an attracting set that's
where it starts and that's really where
it finishes
um I think if you want to think about
um you know how these attracting sets
evolve and contextualize each other you
know you're going to be in a slightly
more
um challenging frame which lots of
people are addressing and it's a really
interesting question I'm not sure
thermodynamics is a right is the right
toolkit to address that to be honest I
think you need to look at more
fundamental maths
um probably important information so at
different scales and think about that
through the lens of say political
biology and evolutionary thinking sure
I'm so glad you read a Quantum
information Theory because that's where
I wanted to go next the
um
the idea and I was wondering if the 300
principle
[Music]
lends any Credence to the idea or has
any relationship to I'm not sure I'm not
sure if you're familiar with um
some theories about the universe being
like a Quantum error correcting code
uh if you're familiar at all with with
that landscape
um but basically it's you know it's a
speculative idea but it looks like
there's some evidence to support it that
the the fabric of space time itself is
actually like a Quantum air correcting
code and when I hear that and I think
about the free entry system Trying to
minimize uncertainty it's trying to you
know
close to air correction or it seems kind
of similar too I wonder if there is a
potential link there and if um if you
have any comments about that or if
you've if that's something that's that's
come across your uh your desk
one day it literally came across my desk
about about um about three or four weeks
ago so somebody sent me this paper on
the University
and I'm delighted uh and um if I
remember the sentiment of the email was
you know it would be great to get this
chips or This Woman's um take on this
you know in relation to a free energy
theoretic formulation because you know
it seemed as if there was a very very
close connection uh uh as you as you
have spotted I I think the best person
to comment upon that would be Chris
Fields um you know so
um you know he you know I I did quantum
physics as a young man that that was 40
years ago I usually defer to the dress
when it comes to
um Quantum information Theory so he's a
he you know he he has a a beautifully
rounded perspective on these things and
we'll probably be able to give you quite
a definite advance so obviously yes it's
the same thing but they're trying to
explain why it's the same thing yeah
it's hard to like
again I will be surprised if all of
these things were weren't entirely
consilient
um yeah and I probably ultimately you
know you probably aren't going to fall
back on something like um James's
maximum and support
um certainly if you're in the public
Quantum information Theory
um you will probably find you know an
equivalent
um description
of the kind we wanted to mention in
terms of variational principles of least
action but you may also find the similar
um explanations in gauge Theory and you
know and ultimately category Theory but
they should all I think be internally
consistent you should be able to sort of
move from one to the other without doing
too much established deal commitments in
anyone your favorite way of framing them
right I'm sure directing universe is is
one example of this yeah it's very much
could be it reminds me too of
Christopher's a frequent collaborator of
his is
um the cognitive scientist Donald
Hoffman I'm not sure if you're familiar
with his work
um I've interviewed him a couple times
on this channel as well but uh one thing
that you said that's
that stood out to me and it's something
that that he he said as well or
something similar is that we don't need
to know the truth we just need to
minimize prediction error you know it's
like this very separate thing I don't
know if you um if you're familiar with
he's got a few different theories I mean
one of which um the fitness speech truth
theorem that we've evolved in order to
basically maximize Fitness instead of to
see what's vertically actually there in
the environment so much what we see is
uh or all of what we see is an illusion
we can never hit he posits that we can
never actually get to
the base reality or the bass truth and
um I'm not sure if you have any thoughts
about that or if it's something that um
you've come across if you've spoken with
Don
no I think that's absolutely right yeah
and it sort of leads you to interesting
discussions uh should you want to go
there in terms of skepticism versus
realism to internalism versus
externalism and the like with
philosophers but yeah certainly from the
point of view of the maths you know the
physics of this kind of sentience it is
all about uh making
um forming or understanding internal
Dynamics as
um encoding some personal probabilistic
Bayesian beliefs about stuff which is
fundamentally hidden Beyond Your Mark of
blanket beyond your sensory Veil it is
inaccessible it is unknowable and I
think probably Chris Fields would frame
this in terms of holographic screens uh
some of the people to the holographic
principle that
um you know ethical exchange of
information across your sensory there or
your Markov blanket can be construed as
a holographic screen from interview of
quantum information Theory and that's
the only way you can entangle or couple
two systems uh you know with classical
information so you know the again we
come back to this fundamental separation
between the inside and the outside which
you know read
um in terms of your your conversations
would be exactly you can never know
what's out there that really don't need
to you know if you can keep your
prediction errors very very small for as
long as you live job done I mean that's
that's perfectly that's that's perfectly
okay it does it does raise the
interesting issue though is there an
outside uh which which will be a more
philosophical issue so both Chris and I
I think would have to commit to the fact
that it probably is an outside in order
to uh have
um to actually be able to read and write
to your holographic screen or to be able
to transact with an environment uh you
know in terms of in both directions over
your markup plan blanket so the strategy
principle puts into slightly ambiguous
position when it comes to philosophy so
on the one hand you can be entirely
skeptical everything that needs to be
done uh is beneath your Markov blanket
within the skull bound brain uh there is
nothing else
um on the other hand that you're you're
making sense of signals that are
provided by something out there so you
have to you have to commit to at least a
mathematical discouragement of stuff
being out there whether something is
sure I'm just looking at the time and I
realized we've gone way over here we had
sort of uh planned out to go I hope I
hope you've enjoyed this discussion I
mean I've gotten so much out of it
um professor and thank you so much
anything else you want to um
I mean I I literally have so many
questions I could continue to ask you
but I do want to be mindful of your time
and energy as well so please let me know
if you know if you have a few extra
minutes I can ask you a couple more but
if you know if you've reached your limit
please let me know also
please ask ask me two more questions and
then I gotta go and have a nice
cigarette okay oh that sounds nice that
sounds lovely
um yeah one of those once in a while
isn't so bad
um I think okay okay two questions oh
now I have to really narrow it down here
but
um
we'll see it's a little bit
um well one it was so one I'll ask you
is and I'm surprised we actually haven't
touched on it
um active inference which honestly for I
mean maybe the first couple weeks I was
looking into the free energy principle I
actually thought they were the same
thing I actually think it's it's written
in other places I think Wikipedia may be
kind of writes them as equivalent and I
believe active inference is a subset of
the free energy principle or it's like
um well perhaps I mean you could
probably you could definitely do the
best job can you help um separate the
two or help us make a distinction
between the 300 principle and what
active inferences
I think you could be forgiven by by
using them synonymously and certainly
you know that's how it was portrayed I
think in in the in the Wikipedia links
having said that
um yo
in the world of um philosophy
um well it's got to be a little bit
um more rigorous in the way that you um
you frame various offerings uh so
nowadays
um and actually I am and a lot of my
friends
um in the philosophy are also very
careful to distinguish between the free
energy principle which is just a method
so very much like we were talking about
Hamilton's principle of least action as
a method for determining the path of
least action or least effort
um the free energy principle is just
what that what it is it's just a method
it's a tool for describing the most
likely
um kind of active sense making or belief
updating or or
um or as you say active inference and so
it's not falsifiable it's not a theory
it's just a principle is this a tool
it's a method if you apply that to
um purposeful Behavior then you have
active imprints so active infants I
think is an application of the free
energy principle
um to um usually simulate or predict or
emulate or to model
um purposeful sentient Behavior
basically so so I've given you a
long-winded technical answer but so you
you can you can so free energy principle
is is usually for sort of physicists and
philosophers that the fossils like to
shout about it the physicists think it's
probably quite quite trivial
um the uh but active inference is more
an application that you might want to
actually apply if you're you're a
a psychologist or artificial
intelligence research and wanting to
emulate this kind of behavior or
understand say a given subject's
Behavior by fitting an active inference
model to that that subject's behavior
using a much more magical way and you
can regard
as only having utility in that ability
to
um
simulate active infants just technically
um the only thing you get from the free
energy principle is really a way of
writing down the Dynamics of
self-organization as a gradient flow on
the
um on the generative model on those
prior preferences on the proper
description of those attracting sets
um which means instead of just looking
at the way a system behaves given its
Dynamics and trying to reverse engineer
its lagrangian uh what you could do is
actually write down a little longer as a
change in constraint as a set of Prior
preferences and then just apply the
rules of the free energy principle to
simulate the behavior of a system that
self-organizes to that set of attracting
States on that particular set of
preferred States and that's basically
what we do in computational uh
neuroscience and machine learning
research okay thank you very much that
helps the distinction is super helpful
um right now last question uh did you I
had to kind of bunch of different ones
I'm like oh I forgot to ask them about
attractor Landscapes and strange
loopiness but I will instead ask you
um if you this is more of a meta this is
personal question but um if you could
give your 20 year old 20 year old self
one piece of advice what would it be so
if you go back
my 20 year old um
I think
I think it would um no I I I'm trying to
be too clever about this
um
probably probably to go to the dentist
more often to me
less trivial answer
um
I I think it would be
would have been nice to do a couple of
years of philosophy as uh yeah I always
say when people when my children and
when my students and when other people
ask me what you know what's good career
advice is keeping your options open you
use that phase earlier on today and I
think there's something quite
fundamental about that as broad found a
foundation as possible bearing in mind
that we are all quintessentially curious
creatures and therefore if you commit to
an academic career you are indulging
that but the best way to explore is to
have a you know a very broad Foundation
um and I managed to do that to a certain
extent but I I didn't I did miss out on
a lot of history and a lot of philosophy
and I remember one of my mentors Jerry
Adelman uh used to refer to me and I
won't say fondly he just used to refer
to me as an intellectual Thug because
of my lack of scholarly
had very little finesse when it comes to
sort of uh fantastic or history so it
would have been nice I don't know what
would have happened if I if I'd spend
time doing that but it would have been
nice just to indulge myself with a
couple years in that kind of training
sure to have that base but yes there's
still time I mean it's not like you know
I mean I'm sure you're busy so you don't
have too much free time but you know
it's always available
foreign
thank you so much this has been
I mean this has been amazing speaking
with you and um I'm so honored so
blessed that you take the time to speak
with me and I I'm sure the audience will
appreciate
um everything here and I'll include
links in the description of this video
for people who want to learn more who
want to read your papers I'll link some
of your papers and some of your um uh
some of your presentations and uh yeah
thanks again it's a treat
oh thank you our village by talking to
you and I'm going to find out how long
we've been talking I deliberately
haven't looked I shouldn't have said
anything I wish I hadn't said anything
now because I could have asked you about
a tractor Landscapes but no yeah it has
been a while and I appreciate so
appreciate you going over
all right I should go away thinking
about
um
um attractive Landscapes and what I
should have advised myself to do when I
was 20 years of age that's a great
question
all right